Papers of Captain Frederick Doten
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Papers of Captain Frederick Doten
June 1863-April 1865
Captain Frederick Doten
BHC-MSS 022
0.2085 linear feet 1 box
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Serving as an officer for Company F, 14th Connecticut, Captain Frederick Doten experienced fighting at Antietam and Gettysburg, and spent time in Libby Prison. His letters to his girlfriend, Georgia, offer an intimate view into both daily life of a Civil War officer and the horrors of the war. In several cases, letters were sent every other day.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased in 1994.
Biography
Captain Frederick Bartlett Doten was born on December 9, 1841 in Sheffield, Massachusetts. The eldest son of Bartlett and Augusta, Frederick was educated in both the town where he was born, and in Bridgeport, Connecticut.
It is unclear when Frederick elected to move to New York City for work, but it is known that he had been a clerk at a carriage manufacturing company in the city until the American Civil War began. He enlisted with the 14th regiment of Connecticut on April 1, 1862, first being placed in Company A. He was promoted to 2nd lieutenant, being moved to Company F upon that promotion. He soon thereafter was promoted to 1st lieutenant, then Captain which saw him return to Company A.
Frederick was present for many key battles of the war, including Antietam and Gettysburg. He was captured at Morton's Ford and sent to Libby Prison in February of 1864, only to be a part of a prisoner exchange in March of 1864.
With the conclusion of the war, Doten was mustered out in May 1865, returning first to Bridgeport and then to New York City to work in carriage manufacturing again. He married Georgiana L. Wells, whom he had written to extensively in the war, on October 4, 1866.
The couple moved back to Massachusetts in 1871, and lived a quiet life. Members of the local Unitarian church, Frederick was a part of the choir. It is unclear if the two had any children.
Frederick Doten died on April 9, 1903. He is buried in Unitarian Cemetery, Marblehead, MA
Scope and Content of Collection
The letters cover a period of 1863 to 1865, with a bulk focusing on October 1864-April 1865. All written to his then girlfriend, later wife Georgiana Wells, the letters discuss both the daily responsibilities of an officer during the American Civil War, and the horrors of what Doten witnessed as the war neared its end.
Arrangement
Chronological
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Connecticut Volunteer Infantry Regiment, 14th (1862-1865).; American Civil War--United States.; American Civil War--United States--Collected Correspondence.; Connecticut--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Connecticut--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental histories.
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, June 4, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, May, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, June 28, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, July 5, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July 8, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July 12, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, July 18, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, September 23, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, September 29, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, October 10, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, October 18, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, October 20, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, October 24, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, November 11, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, November 13, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, November 17, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, November 19, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, November 23, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, November 25, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, December 14, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, December 18, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, December 22, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, December 24, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, December 26, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, January 1, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, January 3, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, January 5, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, January 11, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, January 25, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, January 27, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, January 29, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, January 31, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, February 2, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, February 4, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, February 11, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, February 12, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, February 16, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, February 25, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, February 27, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, March 1, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, March 7, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, March 15, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, March 19, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, March 24, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, March 28, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, March 31, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, April 12, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, April 24, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Envelope, February 12, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Envelope, February 16, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 50)